The death toll is at 5 with 34 injured in the fire
Nowy bilans pożaru
at the Fredrich Emmanuel Library at Munich University.
to pięć ofiar śmiertelnych i 34 rannych.
A grueling search for the missing is still underway.
Wciąż trwa mozolne poszukiwanie zaginionych.
We had a chance to speak with some of the survivors. Let's take a look.
Mieliśmy okazję porozmawiać z ocalałymi. Zapraszamy.
Before I knew what was happening, we were surrounded by flames.
Zanim się zorientowałem, spowiły nas płomienie.
The place was filled with smoke and I couldn't breathe.
Budynek wypełnił się dymem i nie mogłam oddychać.
I thought I was a goner.
Myślałam, że umrę.
A man saved us. He was an Asian man.
Uratował nas mężczyzna. Azjata.
Is he all right?
Nic mu nie jest?
He shot the door hinges with his gun and opened the door for us!
Strzelił bronią w zawiasy i otworzył drzwi!
If it weren't for him, a lot more people would have died.
Gdyby nie on, zginęłoby dużo więcej ludzi.
The police have determined
Policja ustaliła,
that this fire was deliberately set with kerosene and gasoline.
że było to celowe podpalenie z użyciem nafty i benzyny.
They've announced that they're doing everything possible to find the arsonist.
Podjęto szeroko zakrojone działania, aby ustalić tożsamość podpalacza.
The Hell In His Eyes
ROZDZIAŁ 39 PIEKŁO W JEGO OCZACH
It's been burned to ashes.
Spalone na popiół.
I guess all this human wisdom doesn't amount to much when it's all burned up.
Ludzka wiedza na niewiele się zda, gdy wszystko staje w płomieniach.
Any fingerprints on the sniper rifle that was found?
Znaleziono jakieś odciski na karabinie?
I doubt we'll find any after it's been through this fire.
Po tym pożarze raczej nic nie znajdziemy.
But it is definitely a Mauser SR93, just like the one bought by
To na pewno Mauser SR93, identyczny z tym,
After a fire like this, it's unlikely we'll find a trace of the arsonist.
Po takim pożarze ciężko będzie ustalić tożsamość podpalacza.
Every crime scene has evidence.
Każde miejsce zbrodni zawiera dowody.
Here's a cufflink.
Spinka.
Have it analyzed.
Niech to przeanalizują.
Oh, okay.
Dobrze.
Someone was here.
Ktoś tu był.
There's not a human around
Każdy człowiek
who can be somewhere without leaving a trace of their presence.
zostawia zawsze za sobą ślady.
If they can do that, then they're not human.
Jeśli udało im się nie zostawić, nie są ludźmi.
But if by chance they didn't leave any trace, then what are they?
Jeśli nie zostawili żadnych śladów, kim wtedy są?
A demon.
Demonami.
But those don't exist in this world.
Ale one tak naprawdę nie istnieją.
Therefore, anyone who commits a crime can be arrested.
Dlatego można schwytać każdego przestępcę.
Can I speak with Schuwald?
Mogę porozmawiać z Schuwaldem?
He's in intensive care now.
Jest na oddziale intensywnej terapii.
His burns weren't that bad,
Nie poparzył się zbyt mocno,
but considering his age, they've decided not to allow visitors.
ale z racji wieku odwiedziny są wykluczone.
-Let's talk to him. -Huh?
- Porozmawiajmy z nim. - Co?
I cannot allow this!
Nie zezwalam!
I cannot let you see him!
Nie wolno go odwiedzać!
He's conscious, right? We'll be through in a matter of minutes.
Jest przytomny, prawda? To nam zajmie parę minut.
Mr. Schuwald is in an extreme state of shock!
Pan Schuwald jest w potężnym szoku!
He must rest for the time being.
Musi na razie odpoczywać.
Who's that?
Kto to?
That's Mr. Schuwald's son.
Syn pana Schuwalda.
I'm sorry about what happened to your father.
Przykro mi z powodu pana ojca.
I'm Lunge from the BKA.
Jestem Lunge, śledczy federalny z BKA.
I told the police earlier that there was someone
Mówiłem już policji,
I want them to look for.
że muszą kogoś odszukać.
Who's this?
Kto to jest?
He's the man who tried to assassinate your father.
Człowiek, który próbował zabić pana ojca.
You honestly don't know him?
Naprawdę go pan nie zna?
No, I don't. But he might.
Nie. Może on coś wie.
Who's "he"?
Kto taki?
That's what I wanted to tell you!
Do tego zmierzałem!
You've got to find Johan Liebert!
Musi pan znaleźć Johana Lieberta!
Johan Liebert…
Johana Lieberta…
Johan was also at the ceremony with my father!
Był z moim ojcem na ceremonii!
But I can't find him anywhere.
Nigdzie nie mogę go znaleźć.
Johan.
Johan.
Johan Liebert.
Johan Liebert.
All right. We'll start searching for him right away.
Dobrze. Od razu rozpoczniemy poszukiwania.
This is the place that Johan Liebert was renting.
Johan Liebert wynajmował to mieszkanie.
He moved out about two weeks ago.
Wyprowadził się dwa tygodnie temu.
There was no record of him at the law school.
Nie ma śladu w aktach, jakoby studiował prawo.
He wasn't really a student.
Nie był tak naprawdę studentem.
Have you contacted his parents who live in Offenbach?
Kontaktowałeś się z jego rodzicami w Offenbachu?
That was a dead end as well.
To też był martwy trop.
They are almost rarely spoke with neighbors.
Rzadko rozmawiali z sąsiadami.
Do you want us to dust this place for fingerprints?
Mamy poszukać odcisków?
-I doubt you'll find any. -What?
- Wątpię, żebyś je znalazł. - Co?
No record of his presence.
Nie ma dowodów jego obecności.
I've never seen anything like this.
To dla mnie nowość.
This place feels as if nobody has ever lived here.
To miejsce sprawia wrażenie, jakby nikt tu nigdy nie mieszkał.
Yeah.
Tak.
I am Johan.
Jestem Johanem.
I am Johan Liebert.
Jestem Johanem Liebertem.
Who am I?
Kim jestem?
I was here.
Byłem tutaj.
But I don't exist.
Ale ja nie istnieję.
Am I a demon?
Czy jestem demonem?
I'm sorry for making you worry about me, Lotte.
Przepraszam, że cię zmartwiłam, Lotte.
You better believe I was worried.
Żebyś wiedziała!
They kept pulling people out of there, but you never came out.
Wciąż wyciągałam stamtąd osoby, ale nigdy nie wyszłaś.
I was so afraid for you.
Martwiłam się o ciebie.
With those injuries, I'm surprised you made it out of that fire on your own.
Z takimi obrażeniami dziwię się, że sama uratowałaś się z pożaru.
The firemen were surprised too.
Strażacy też byli zaskoczeni.
Someone helped me.
Ktoś mi pomógł.
Someone helped you?
Ktoś ci pomógł?
You were the last person to come out, you know.
Przecież wyszłaś jako ostatnia.
A Japanese man…
Japończyk…
Wasn't a Japanese doctor taken to one of the hospitals?
Nie zabrano japońskiego lekarza do jednego ze szpitali?
There were several Japanese people,
Było trochę Japończyków,
but I think they were all businessmen.
ale to chyba sami biznesmeni.
That's not possible.
Niemożliwe.
Really?
Naprawdę?
You see, I was trapped beneath a curtain when he found me…
Przygniatała mnie kotara, kiedy mnie znalazł…
Nina!
Nino!
I'm sure of it.
Jestem tego pewna.
He was there.
On tam był.
Attendees of the ceremony reported that
Uczestnicy ceremonii donieśli,
just before the fire, you told everyone to evacuate immediately.
że tuż przed pożarem kazał pan wszystkim niezwłocznie się ewakuować.
Why did you say that?
Dlaczego tak pan powiedział?
You must have realized something was about to happen.
Musiał pan mieć świadomość, że coś się stanie.
Isn't that right, Mr. Schuwald?
Prawda, panie Schuwald?
I think that's about enough.
Chyba już wystarczy.
Also, do you know this man?
Zna pan tego człowieka?
Can you see it if I hold it this close?
Widzi pan, gdy trzymam tak blisko?
This man attempted to assassinate you.
Stał za próbą zamachu na pana.
Some witnesses say he was at the library.
Świadkowie mówią, że był w bibliotece.
According to witnesses, they say that this man saved people.
Twierdzą też, że ten człowiek uratował ludzi.
That's enough. I'm putting an end to this.
Dość tego. Nie pozwalam na więcej.
If he remembers anything, call me right away.
Jeśli coś sobie przypomni, proszę o kontakt.
One more thing.
Jeszcze jedno.
Do you know the whereabouts of your secretary, Johan Liebert?
Wie pan, gdzie przebywa pana sekretarz, Johan Liebert?
That's enough! Get out now!
Wystarczy! Wynoście się!
He's gone completely senile.
Całkowicie zniedołężniał.
After going through something like that at his age, it's no wonder.
Nic dziwnego. Po takim przejściu w tym wieku.
I guess this is the end of the road for the financial kingpin,
To koniec drogi dla finansowego magnata,
the Vampire of Bavaria.
Wampira z Bawarii.
-No, it's not. -What?
- Nieprawda. - Co?
I could tell from his eyes that he understood everything.
Widziałem po oczach, że wszystko rozumiał.
Really?
Naprawdę?
Let's talk to some of the other witnesses.
Porozmawiajmy z innymi świadkami.
Do you have a list of the victims?
Masz listę ofiar?
Yes, I do.
Tak.
What do you think is going on anyway?
Twoim zdaniem, co się dzieje?
I mean, witnesses said that someone who looks like Tenma rescued people.
Według świadków ktoś podobny do Tenmy uratował ludzi.
Do you think it could be a case of multiple personalities?
Myślisz, że to przypadek rozdwojenia jaźni?
"Nina"…
„Nina”…
"Nina Fortner."
„Nina Fortner”.
Does that name ring a bell?
To nazwisko brzmi znajomo?
Nina Fortner was released this morning.
Ninę Fortner wypuszczono rano.
The address on the police record was fake. What's in the hospital records?
Adres w aktach policji był fałszywy. Co podają dokumenty szpitalne?
Hold on. I'll look it up.
Moment. Już sprawdzam.
Nina Fortner.
Nina Fortner.
Same name as the daughter of the Fortners who was killed in Heidelberg.
To nazwisko córki Fortnerów, których zabito w Heidelbergu.
She's currently missing.
Uważana jest za zaginioną.
Thank you for sharing such a painful story with me.
Dziękuję za podzielenie się tą bolesną historią.
It matches perfectly
Idealnie pasuje to
with the story Tenma told me about what's happened the last ten years.
do wersji wydarzeń Tenmy z ostatnich dziesięciu lat.
Tenma?
Tenmy?
That's right. He came here in his investigation of these cases.
Tak. Przyszedł do mnie w ramach śledztwa nad tymi sprawami.
He soon left so he could assassinate Johan.
Odszedł, żeby przeprowadzić zamach na Johanie.
I believe Tenma was at the library that day to carry out
Wierzę, że Tenma był tego dnia w bibliotece,
his assassination attempt.
żeby dokonać zamachu.
That's why I went there.
Dlatego się tam udałem.
But then there was that fire.
Wybuchł jednak pożar.
Now I don't know if Tenma was even there, let alone Johan.
Teraz nie wiem nawet, czy był tam Tenma, a tym bardziej Johan.
Listen to me, Nina. Stop going after Johan.
Nino, przestań gonić za Johanem.
He's more than you can handle.
Sama mu nie podołasz.
I'd agree that the police aren't much help.
Przyznaję, że policja jest mało pomocna.
We need to proceed slowly and carefully in this fight.
Musimy kroczyć powoli i ostrożnie w tej walce.
Someday, the truth will come out.
Kiedyś prawda wyjdzie na jaw.
Don't you worry. We'll help you.
Nie bój się niczego. Pomożemy ci.
You must be exhausted.
Musisz być wycieńczona.
Why don't you rest here for the time being?
Może teraz odpoczniesz?
-He was there. -What?
- Był tam. - Co?
He was definitely there at the library then.
Na pewno był w bibliotece.
Tenma was there.
Tenma tam był.
You should eat.
Powinnaś coś zjeść.
Thank you, Dieter.
Dziękuję, Dieterze.
Those are Kaiser rolls.
Proszę, kajzerki.
I've put roasted ham and Gouda cheese on them.
Z szynką i goudą.
That's Tenma's favorite.
Tenma je uwielbia.
I appreciate this.
Dziękuję.
-It's delicious. -Really?
- Pyszne. - Naprawdę?
Yes. Good food makes me feel better.
Tak. Dobre jedzenie poprawia mi nastrój.
Tenma always said that too.
Tenma też to powtarzał.
I'd like to see him.
Chciałabym go zobaczyć.
I'd like to see Tenma.
Chciałabym zobaczyć Tenmę.
Me too.
Ja też.
The weather's looking nice again.
Pogoda znów dopisuje.
I have an idea. How about we take a trip when you're better?
Mam pomysł. Pojedźmy na wycieczkę, jak wrócisz do sił.
A trip to Asia might be nice.
Fajnie byłoby odwiedzić Azję. Taka idealna odmiana.
You know, you should really take it easy more often now.
Powinieneś się teraz oszczędzać.
Dad, you've worked long and hard enough already.
Tato, dość się już naharowałeś w życiu.
A bridge…
Most…
What?
Co?
Three frogs…
Trzy żaby…
What's that? What are you trying to say?
Co próbujesz powiedzieć?
There were three frogs…
Były trzy żaby…
What?
Co?
In his eyes…
W jego oczach…
His eyes?
Oczach?
I could see hell…
Widziałem piekło…
in his eyes.
w jego oczach.
I could see hell in the eyes of a living human.
Widziałem piekło w oczach żyjącej osoby.
Karl.
Karlu.
Yes?
Tak?
I have something I want you to tell a certain man.
Mam coś. Przekaż to pewnemu mężczyźnie.
The man is waiting in Dresden.
Czeka w Dreźnie.
In Dresden? What should I tell him?
W Dreźnie? Co mam mu powiedzieć?
Okay.
Dobrze.
So you want me to send that message to the man waiting in Dresden, right?
Mam przekazać tę wiadomość człowiekowi w Dreźnie?
Do you want me to do it now?
Teraz mam to zrobić?
All right. I'll leave immediately.
Dobrze. Już wyruszam.
Karl.
Karlu.
Your mother,
Twoja matka…
she hated me, didn't she?
mnie nienawidziła, prawda?
No. She didn't hate you.
Nie. Nic z tych rzeczy.
Karl, when you return from Dresden,
Karlu, kiedy wrócisz z Drezna,
will you stay with me?
zostaniesz ze mną?
Yes.
Tak.
I'm scared.
Boję się.
Scared of what?
Czego się boisz?
I'm not sure why, but I'm very scared.
Nie wiem dlaczego, ale bardzo się boję.
Try to remember.
Spróbuj sobie przypomnieć. Powoli, nic na siłę.
A town out of a fairytale.
Miasteczko niczym z bajki.
A fairytale town? Where is it?
Bajkowe miasteczko? Gdzie leży?
What did you feel when you looked at this book?
Co czułaś, gdy czytałaś tę książkę?
Tell me whatever comes to mind. Anything at all.
Mów wszystko, co ci przyjdzie do głowy.
Dr. Gillen, be careful.
- Doktorze Gillen, ostrożnie. - Jeszcze trochę.
Stop, please!
Proszę przestać!
Three frogs…
Trzy żaby…
There were three frogs.
Były trzy żaby.
There were three frogs?
Były trzy żaby?
Three frogs?
Trzy żaby?
What are you talking about?
O czym ty mówisz?
The picture…
Obraz…
A picture?
Obraz?
Do you mean they're in this picture book that made Johan faint?
Są w tej książeczce obrazkowej, przez którą Johan zemdlał?
There's no drawing of three frogs anywhere in that book.
- W tej książeczce nie ma trzech żab. - Gdzie widziałaś ten obraz?
That's enough.
Dość tego.
That's all for today.
Wystarczy na dzisiaj.
Okay.
Dobrze.
It was a mistake to hope that Inspector Lunge of the BKA would help us.
Byłem w błędzie, licząc, że inspektor Lunge z BKA nam pomoże.
You're right. I think we should change our strategy too.
Zgadza się. Musimy też zmodyfikować naszą strategię.
Next time we bring evidence to the police,
Gdy następnym razem damy policji dowody,
we should speak directly with his superiors.
trzeba rozmawiać z przełożonymi.
And it should only be evidence that we've taken the time
Ale tylko dowody, które mieliśmy okazję
to thoroughly research.
porządnie zweryfikować.
But how much time should we take?
Ale ile czasu mamy czekać?
The information we have on Johan now is vague and there's far too little.
Nasze obecne informacje o Johanie są mgliste i szczątkowe.
I'm sure that the man Johan worked for, Schuwald, has some information.
Pracodawca Johana, Schuwald, musi coś wiedzieć.
He left for somewhere two days ago, but I can't reach him.
Wyjechał gdzieś dwa dni temu. Jest nieosiągalny.
It's nothing concrete,
Mało to konkretne,
but some of the witnesses said that an Asian man helped them escape.
ale część świadków mówiło, że Azjata pomógł im uciec.
But if Tenma's fingerprints are found on the sniper rifle discovered at the scene,
Jeśli znajdą odciski palców Tenmy na karabinie snajperskim,
no number of witness statements will save him.
żadne zeznania świadków mu nie pomogą.
How long should we wait?
Jak długo mamy czekać?
There's no more time!
Nie ma już czasu!
When the truth becomes clear and the police take action,
Zanim ujawnimy prawdę i policja zareaguje,
by that time…
dojdzie już do tego…
Tenma will…
że Tenma…
Nina.
Nino.
I'm sorry.
Przepraszam.
Nina, I understand very well how you feel.
Dobrze rozumiem twój niepokój.
I lost a close friend of mine, Richard, in all of this.
Przez to wszystko straciłem bliskiego przyjaciela, Richarda.
He had a bright future ahead of him.
Miał przed sobą świetlaną przyszłość.
But Johan cut his future short.
Ale Johan mu to zabrał.
I am not giving up. Never!
Nie poddam się. Nigdy!
Okay, let's eat.
Dobrze, jedzmy.
Three frogs…
Trzy żaby…
Like a town out of a fairy tale…
Niczym miasteczko z baśni…
I know what it is!
Wiem, co to jest!
Dieter…
Dieterze…
I'm going with you.
Idę z tobą.
Don't be silly. You can't go.
Nie wygłupiaj się! Nie możesz.
You stay here. Understand?
Zostań tu. Rozumiesz?
Tell Dr. Reichwein thank you for taking care of me.
Podziękuj ode mnie doktorowi Reichweinowi za opiekę nade mną.
Goodbye.
Żegnaj.
Dieter!
Dieterze!
I want to see him.
Chcę go zobaczyć.
I want to see Tenma!
Chcę zobaczyć Tenmę!
DRESDEN (SAXONY)
DREZNO (SAKSONIA)
Day three and still nothing.
Trzeci dzień i nadal nic.
I'm supposed to wait in the square at the station, but this place is huge.
Mam czekać na placu dworcowym, ale to miejsce jest ogromne.
I don't think I'll be able to meet the man you told me about, Father.
Chyba nie spotkam się z mężczyzną, o którym mi mówiłeś, ojcze.
Karl.
Karl.
You're Karl, aren't you?
Karl, prawda?
Who are you?
Kim pan jest?
The man who was attempting to assassinate your father.
Człowiekiem, który próbował zabić twojego ojca.
Isn't that what the police told you?
Czyż tak nie twierdzi policja?
Yes.
Tak.
I've been watching you from that building for three days.
Obserwuję cię z tego budynku od trzech dni.
It appears the police aren't tailing you.
Policja raczej cię nie śledzi.
Give me the message.
Przekaż mi wiadomość.
Hang in there. We're almost out.
Trzymaj się. Już niedaleko.
Hurry up and get out. The police will be here soon.
Szybko, uciekaj. Policja zaraz tu będzie.
But…
Ale…
Go to Dresden. Wait in the train station square.
Pojedź do Drezna. Zaczekaj na placu dworcowym.
My son Karl will bring you a message.
Mój syn Karl przekaże ci wiadomość.
Give me the message.
Przekaż wiadomość.
This is it.
Proszę.
"Cedok Bridge.The Three Frogs"?
„Most Cedok. Trzy żaby”?
My father also told me this.
Ojciec powiedział mi też to:
"If the monster you are chasing has a twin…"
„Jeśli potwór, którego ścigasz, ma bliźniaczkę…”
The twins' mother is alive and living in Prague.
Matka bliźniąt żyje i mieszka w Pradze.
Grimmer
ROZDZIAŁ 40 GRIMMER